A Guide to the Papers of Hugh Scott, 1930-1987
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Hugh Scott, 1930-1987
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10200-ac, -ad
This collection consists of ca. 3200 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Library by the Honorable Hugh Scott of Falls Church, Virginia, on October 6, 1988 and January 9, 1989.
Scope and Content Information
Family correspondence, 1944-1959, and n.d., includes letters, August-September 1945, from Marian Scott to Hugh Scott serving with the United States Naval Reserve during World War II. The letters begin after the surrender and reveal her thoughts on the war and public thought, in general, and mentions the Japanese surrender and the signing of the treaty. Other letters include one from his father, Hugh D. Scott, to the senator (January 23, 1946) and from Marnie Scott Concannon (March 1959).
Personal correspondence, 1939-1984, and n.d., covers a variety of subjects. A letter, October 17, 1944, from the Salisburys in Herts, England, mentions bomb raids and blackouts in their area. A letter, March 14, 1959, from Mrs. Donald H. Graham, Jr., in Honolulu, Hawaii, discusses Hawaii's new statehood and the celebrations. There is a letter, June 13, 1959, from the President of Ireland, Uachtaran na Heireann, expressing his gratitude for Scott's assistance in securing an invitation from President Eisenhower and for the peoples' warm reception. There is a letter from Park Chung Hee, President of Korea, dated June 24, 1965. Correspondence, 1971-1972, discusses Memorial Acres, a housing project in Sunbury, Pennsylvania, and Marian Scott's appearance at the dedication. On March 1, 1976, Marian Scott writes to Dorothy McCardle, giving an account of time spent with Alice Morrow, Anne Lindbergh's aunt, on board an American export line freighter from Istanbul shortly after the death of the Lindbergh baby.
There is also a letter, December 16, n.y., from Hugh Scott, in Bombay, India, to his staff, describing travel in Ceylon, Kandy, Singapore, and Colombo.
V.I.P. correspondence, 1959-1968, includes letters from U. S. Presidents and other political leaders and their wives, and is arranged alphabetically. Two letters, May 1 and June 22, 1978, from Jimmy Carter discuss the Panama Canal treaties transferring control of the canal to Panama. On October 22, 1962, Everett McKinley Dirksen wrote, following the end of the 87th Congress, his appreciation and gratitude of members. Dwight D. Eisenhower wrote on June 19, 1959, concerning the Philadelphia Independence Hall ceremonies on July Fourth honoring the new flag of the United States, after Alaska was admitted to the Union on January 3. There are also letters from Viscount Hailsham, Douglas McGarel Hogg, in Putney Heath, England (March 15, 1959); Christian A. Herter, Secretary of State (April 24, 1959); Herbert Hoover (November 1, 1949 & August 15, 1959); [Joseph Patrick] Kennedy, Office of the President, in answer to sympathy over the death of Thomas [ ] (December 19, 1961); and, Dean Rusk, Secretary of State, re Scott's appointment to the U. S. Delegation to the Second Special Inter-American Conference at Rio De Janeiro (January 25, 1966). In addition, there is a menu card, May 23, 1968, signed by Lady Bird Johnson, Mamie Doud Eisenhower, Muriel Humphrey, and several senators' wives.
Among the personal papers, 1930-1982, and n.d., are: a memorandum of agreement, October 28, 1930, between Hugh Scott, author, and Cyrus M. Dixon, publisher; "Armchair Verses," a book of limited edition [1958], by Josephine L. Reed Hopwood; and an undated broadside entitled "'The Honor Men' by James Hay, Jr., '03, in 1912 Corks and Curls."
The political papers, 1948-1986, include newspaper clippings, schedules, campaign and election information, and a list of Pennsylvania Senators, 1789-1980.
Photographs of Hugh and Marian Scott with various persons, ca. 1910-1976, include a variety of personal and political friends. Persons or subjects include: Hugh Scott as a Boy Scout (ca. 1910); inscribed photograph of Carroll Reece and Scott (June 27, 1948); Scott and Hugh D. Scott, Sr. (November 25, 1951); Joseph S. Clark and Scott (February 1960); Nixon-Lodge Campaign, GOP Truth Squad Special with Gerald R. Ford, Scott, and others (September-October 1960); NATO (November 13, 1961); University of Virginia Reunion of the Class of 1922 (1962); Seoul, Korea (December 18, 1963); and, Moscow, U. S. S. R., meeting with Suslov, Chief of Foreign Affairs (August 20, 1969). Undated photographs include family photographs and miscellaneous campaigns, political affairs, and organizations.
V. I. P. photographs, 1948-1985, include numerous political figures. Included are: Margaret Chase Smith (1948); Pope Pius XII (1956); Everett M. Dirksen (1960); Richard M. Nixon (1960, 1972-1974); Lyndon B. Johnson (1964); John G. Tower (1973-1974); Gerald R. Ford (1973-1974); Barry Goldwater (1974); John J. Rhodes (1974); Mike Mansfield (1974); Hubert H. Humphrey (1974); Thomas P. "Tip" O'Neill, Jr. (1974); Nelson A. Rockefeller (1974-1975); and Juan Carlos (1985). Among the undated V. I. P. photographs are Margaret Chase Smith, Robert Dole, Mike Mansfield, Edward M. Kennedy, George Romney, John G. Tower, Betty Ford, Barry Goldwater, John J. Rhodes, Teddy Kollek, and Alf M. Landon.
Other photographs are of people and scenes in China, and include Chou-En-Lai, Chou-Pei-Yuan, and Ko Mo Jo; and Scott's naval service which includes Tokyo, Tokyo Bay, U.S.S. Mt. Olympus, Charles Philip Hall (1886-1953), Jap[anese] Liaison Committee for Surrender, Yokohama (Japan), Manila, John M[adison] Hoskins (1898-1964), U.S.S. Valley Forge, and U.S.S. Seadragon.
Among the bound volumes is a travel journal, 1932, kept by Marian Huntington Chase Scott while onboard the S.S. Examiner. They set sail on March 19 from New York, traveling to Africa and Europe, including Spain, France, Italy, Greece, Turkey, Roumania, and Morocco. Topics discussed include "Scottie" [Hugh Scott] and other passengers, life onboard, and places visited. Other items in this series are honorary certificates in covers, 1964-1987.
Memorabilia includes awards of recognition in the form of statues, plaques, and bowls; and, campaign materials such as buttons, tie tacks and pins, and matchbooks. Also included are two gavels: One engraved "Congressman Gerald R. Ford/Permanent Chairman/Republican National Convention/Miami Beach Florida 1972"; and, one engraved "Presented to THE HONORABLE HUGH SCOTT ... in recognition of his distinguished service to the republic/May 17, 1982 --- Washington, D.C."
Contents List
- CORRESPONDENCE AND PAPERS
  - Correspondence: Family 1944-1959, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Personal 1939-1984, n.d. (Box 1)
  - V.I.P. Correspondence 1959-1968 (Box 1)
  - Certificates and Citations 1944-1987 (Box 1)
  - Naval Papers 1941-1951 (Box 1)
  - Personal Papers 1930-1982, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Political Papers 1948-1986 (Box 1)
- PHOTOGRAPHS: PEOPLE
  - Hugh and Marian Scott with various persons 1910-1976, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Hugh and Marian Scott with various persons n.d. (Box 1)
  - Hugh and Marian Scott with various persons n.d., 3 folders (Box 2)
  - V.I.P.s 1948-1985 (Box 2)
- PHOTOGRAPHS: PLACES
  - China 1970s (Box 2)
  - England 1976 (Box 2)
  - Indonesia n.d. (Box 2)
  - Naval Service 1945-1962, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Philippines: American Embassy in Manila (Box 2)
- BOUND VOLUMES
  - Travel Journal kept by Marian Huntington Chase Scott while on board the S. S. Examiner 1932 (Box 3)
  - Honorary Certificates 1964-1987, 6 items (Box 3)
- PHOTOGRAPH FILE BOXES
  - Bath, England 1973 (Box 4)
  - Bangkok, Thailand 1972 (Box 4)
  - Bergen, Norway 1973 (Box 4)
  - Caracas, Venezuela [1972] (Box 4)
  - Chiang Mai, Thailand 1972 (Box 4)
  - China 1972 (Box 4)
  - Copenhagen, Denmark 1973 (Box 4)
  - England 1969, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Greece 1974 (Box 4)
  - Georgia, U.S.S.R. 1974 (Box 4)
  - Hong Kong 1972 (Box 4)
  - Indonesia 1972 (Box 4)
  - Indonesia: Jogjakarta 1972 (Box 4)
  - Oslo, Norway 1973 (Box 4)
  - Rio [de Janeiro], Brazil n.d. (Box 4)
  - Singapore, Malaysia 1972 (Box 4)
  - Mexico 1974 (Box 5)
  - Romania and Bulgaria 1974 (Box 5)
  - St. Maartens, Leeward Islands, West Indies n.d. (Box 5)
  - Soviet Union 1974 (Box 5)
  - Holland 1975 (Box 5)
  - Belgium [1975] (Box 5)
  - Bermuda 1975 (Box 5)
  - Brussels, Belgium; Berlin, Germany; Madrid, Spain: Interparliamentary Union Trip 1975 (Box 5)
  - Russia: Interparliamentary Union Trip 1975 (Box 5)
  - Poland 1975 (Box 5)
  - Spain: Madrid and Toledo [1975] (Box 5)
  - Brazil 1965 (Box 5)
  - Nepal, Istanbul, Turkey; Rome, Italy; India 1957 (Box 5)
  - Interparliamentary Union 1966 (Box 5)
  - Korea n.d. (Box 5)
  - Mallorca 1967 (Box 5)
  - Hong Kong, Japan, Istanbul 1967 (Box 5)
  - Italy n.d. (Box 5)
- MEMORABILIA
  - Plaques and License Plates 1957-1986 (Box 6)
  - Gavel (Gerald R. Ford); campaign buttons, tie tacks and pins, and matchbooks; awards of recognition 1950s-1980s (Box 7)
  - Civil Rights Award; Bowl presented by the Republic of Korea; Philadelphia Bowl 1963-[1976] (Box 8)
  - Plaques: Korean War Veterans 1975; U.S. Senate Bicentennial Year 1976; Randolph-Macon College 1978; Lions International 1983. Framed Photographs with Pens used by the President: John Fitzgerald Kennedy 1961; Lyndon Baines Johnson 1964, 1965, 1966, 1968. 1961-1983 (Box 9)
  - State of New York Warrant signed by Franklin D. Roosevelt 1932 Jan 7 (Oversize S-22)
  - Congressional Certificates and Citations 1940-1987 (Oversize S-22)
  - Legal Admittances 1922-1924 (Oversize S-22)
  - Fraternity Citations: Alpha Chi Rho, Alpha Phi Omega 1969-1980, n.d. (Oversize S-22)
  - Randolph-Macon and University of Virginia 1958-1985 (Oversize S-22)
  - Honorary Degrees presented to Hugh Scott by Colleges and Universities 1959-1977 (Oversize S-22)
  - Life Memberships in Associations 1958-1986 (Oversize S-22)
  - Miscellaneous Associations and Groups: Awards, Certificates, and Citations 1944-1978 (Oversize S-22)
  - Photographs of Hugh and Marian Scott and Political Figures, including U. S. Presidents 1948-1975, n.d., 2 folders (Oversize S-23)
  - Autograph Photographs of Political Figures, including Richard Nixon, Jimmy Carter, Dwight D. Eisenhower, and Gerald R. Ford 1966-1977, n.d. (Oversize S-24)
  - Miscellaneous Printed, including Asian newspapers, magazines re the Dewey and Warren campaign and the deaths of Winston Churchill and John F. Kennedy 1947-1963 (Oversize S-24)
  - Honorary Degrees presented to Hugh Scott by Colleges and Universities 1955-1986 (Oversize T-10)
  - Miscellaneous ca. 1920-1971 (Oversize T-10)
    - Photograph: University of Virginia Class, ca. 1920 ca. 1920
    - Photograph: "Virginia Reel Board, 1921-1922" 1921-1922
    - Photograph: United Statesnuclear test sight, Bikini Atoll in Pacific ca. 1946
    - "Goodwill Messages from around the World brought to the Moon by the Astronauts of Apollo 11" July 20, 1969
  - Cartoon: "Li'l Abner" cartoons by Al Capp, with caricature of Hugh Scott and Hubert Humphrey September 20, 1971, Inscribed by AC to HS (Oversize T-10)
  - Cartoon: "Great Scott! -- LBJ Landslide" by Hungerford n.d., 2 copies, one inscribed by HS (Oversize T-10)
  - "Nixon's Shattered Presidency--Time" 1974 May 20
  - The Baronial Order of Magna Charta pronouncing Hugh Scott as a lineal descendant of one or more of the twenty-five Barons of England 1982 Jan 9
  - The Baronial Order of Magna Charta --Magna Charta Day Award 1985 June 16
  - Testimonial dinner in honor of Hugh Scott, held at the Bellevue [Hotel]. Principal address by U. S. Senator Jacob Javitts. 1964 Oct 20 (Othertype T-905)